You know, when I look at what's
happening in Washington right now with
this government shutdown, I see
something much deeper than the typical
partisan theater we've become accustomed
to over the past few decades. I've spent
my career studying economic policy,
advising governments around the world.
And I can tell you with absolute
certainty that what we're witnessing
isn't just a political standoff between
Democrats and Republicans. It's a
symptom of a much more profound
dysfunction in how America governs
itself and frankly how we've lost sight
of what responsible fiscal policy
actually means. Let me start with some
context that I think is essential for
understanding this moment. According to
PBS NewsHour reporting from early
October, the government shutdown began
after Senate Democrats refused to
advance a Republican continuing
resolution with a key vote failing 54 to
44, well short of the 60 votes needed to
overcome a filibuster. Now, on the
surface, this looks like standard
Washington gridlock. But when you dig
into the details, you begin to see
something more troubling about how both
parties are approaching the fundamental
task of governance. The Republicans are
saying they want a clean continuing
resolution, something short and simple
to keep the government running. The
Democrats, according to multiple news
sources, including NPR and Axios, are
demanding extensions of Affordable Care
Act subsidies that are set to expire
along with reversals of certain health
care cuts. Now, both sides have framed
this as a matter of principle. The
Republicans say they're being fiscally
responsible. The Democrats say they're
protecting health care for millions of
Americans. And you know what? I've heard
these arguments before, many times under
different administrations with different
actors, and the script barely changes.
But here's what troubles me. is an
economist who has studied fiscal policy
for over 40 years. Neither side is
actually addressing the core problem,
which is that the United States has been
running massive budget deficits for
decades, spending far beyond our means,
and funding this profleacy through a
combination of borrowing and monetary
expansion that will eventually come home
to roost. When I see Republicans talk
about fiscal responsibility while
simultaneously supporting trillions in
tax cuts that overwhelmingly benefit the
wealthy, I have to question whether this
is genuine concern about the budget or
political positioning. And when I see
Democrats demanding expanded healthcare
subsidies without explaining how we're
going to pay for our existing
commitments to Social Security,
Medicare, and Medicaid as our population
ages, I have to ask the same question.
Let me be very clear about something and
this is important for everyone to
understand especially those of you who
remember the America of the 1950s60s and
70s when government actually functioned
reasonably well. The federal budget
deficit is not caused by Democrats being
too generous or Republicans being too
stingy. It's caused by a political
system that has been captured by special
interests on both sides. We cut taxes
for the wealthy and corporations which
drains revenue. We spend trillions on
military interventions around the world
that have nothing to do with American
security and everything to do with
maintaining a global empire that serves
corporate interests. We allow health
care costs to spiral out of control
because we refuse to implement the kinds
of cost containment measures that every
other advanced economy uses successfully
and we refuse to have an honest
conversation with the American people
about these trade-offs. Now, according
to the White House's own statements from
October 1st, the administration has
characterized this as a Democratic
shutdown, claiming that Democrats are
holding funding hostage to force through
what they call a partisan wish list. The
Republican narrative, as reported by
Representative Pete Stalber and echoed
across conservative media, is that
Democrats want funding for priorities
that have nothing to do with keeping
essential government services running.
They point to demands for health care
benefits for undocumented immigrants,
funding for media outlets, climate
initiatives, and other programs that
could be addressed in separate
legislation. On the other side, Senate
Minority Leader Chuck Schumer, as
reported by multiple outlets, including
CBS News and NPR, has been saying that
the government is shut down because
Republicans would rather kick 15 million
people off health insurance than
negotiate in good faith. He's framed
this as a health care crisis, pointing
out that families are receiving notices
about premium increases right now and
that the expiration of these tax credits
will cause real hardship for real
people. So, who's right? Well, from my
perspective as someone who tries to look
at these issues through the lens of
economic analysis rather than partisan
loyalty, I'd say they're both wrong in
fundamental ways and they're both
revealing the same underlying disease in
American governance. Let me explain what
I mean. First, on the Republican side,
this notion that we can achieve fiscal
responsibility through short-term
continuing resolutions while maintaining
massive military budgets, while keeping
tax rates on the wealthy at historic
lows, while refusing to address the
structural drivers of health care costs
is simply not credible. I've written
extensively about how America's trade
deficit, which so many politicians love
to complain about, is actually a direct
consequence of our budget deficit. When
the government spends more than it takes
in, that excess demand has to be met
through imports. It's basic
macroeconomics.
uh you cannot run persistent budget
deficits of a trillion dollars or more
per year, which we've been doing, and
then act surprised when we have trade
deficits and when other countries end up
holding massive amounts of American
debt. The Republicans like to talk about
being the party of fiscal
responsibility. But where was this
concern when they passed major tax cuts
in recent years? Where is this concern
when it comes to military spending,
which has grown to over 800 billion
dollars annually, more than the next 10
countries combined? I spent years
working with countries around the world
on economic development, and I can tell
you that no successful economy devotes
such an enormous share of its resources
to the military unless it's actively
fighting an existential war. We're not.
We're maintaining a global empire that
serves the interests of defense
contractors and a foreign policy
establishment that has led us into one
disastrous intervention after another
from Iraq to Libya to Afghanistan,
wasting trillions of dollars and
hundreds of thousands of lives in the
process. So when Republicans say they
want a clean continuing resolution
because they care about fiscal
responsibility, I have to say with all
due respect, that's not a comprehensive
fiscal policy. That's political theater.
A real fiscally responsible approach
would involve confronting the defense
lobby, reforming the tax code to ensure
that wealthy individuals and
corporations pay their fair share, and
working with Democrats on healthc care
reform that actually reduces costs
rather than just shifting who pays for
them. Now, let me turn to the Democratic
position because I think they deserve
equally critical scrutiny. According to
the Washington Monthly's analysis, uh,
which actually defended Schumer's
approach, the Democrats have maintained
unity in opposing the Republican
continuing resolution demanding healthc
care protections as the price for their
votes. Schumer has been quoted saying
that the Affordable Care Act tax credits
are essential, that allowing them to
expire would cause premiums to increase
by thousands of dollars for millions of
Americans, and that this is a moral
issue that Democrats cannot compromise
on. I understand that argument. I've
spent much of my career advocating for
universal health care, for systems that
ensure everyone has access to medical
care regardless of their ability to pay.
The United States is the only advanced
economy that doesn't guarantee health
care as a right. And the result is that
we spend far more per capita than any
other country while achieving worse
health outcomes. So yes, protecting
healthcare subsidies matters. But here's
my problem with how the Democrats are
approaching this. They're treating the
Affordable Care Act subsidies as if
they're a permanent solution to
America's health care crisis when in
reality they're a band-aid on a
fundamentally broken system. We don't
have a functioning healthcare market in
the United States. We have a system
dominated by insurance companies,
pharmaceutical corporations, and
hospital chains that extract enormous
profits while delivering mediocre care
at exorbitant prices. The subsidies help
people afford insurance, yes, but they
do nothing to address the underlying
cost drivers. They're essentially a
transfer of taxpayer money to the health
care industry. Every other advanced
economy has figured out how to provide
universal health care at a fraction of
what we spend. They do it through
various models. Singlepayer systems like
in Canada and the UK, social insurance
systems like in Germany and France. But
the common thread is that they all
involve much more government regulation
of prices, much more emphasis on primary
care and prevention, and much less
tolerance for the kind of profit-seeking
behavior that dominates American
healthcare. If Democrats were serious
about health care, they would be pushing
for fundamental reform, not just
fighting to preserve subsidies that prop
up a dysfunctional system. Moreover, and
this is crucial, the Democrats need to
be honest with the American people about
fiscal realities. We have an aging
population, the baby boom generation,
and I'm part of that generation. We're
retiring now in massive numbers. Social
Security and Medicare costs are going to
increase substantially over the next two
decades. At the same time, we have
enormous needs for infrastructure
investment, for transitioning to clean
energy, to address climate change, for
education, for research and development.
These are all important priorities, but
we cannot fund all of them while
maintaining low taxes on the wealthy,
while spending 800 billion on the
military, while allowing health care
costs to spiral upward unchecked.
Something has to give. and the Democrats
unwillingness to have that honest
conversation, their tendency to promise
expansions of social programs without
explaining how we'll pay for them
contributes to the fiscal
irresponsibility that plagues both
parties. I wrote in Common Dreams and
other outlets about how President
Trump's tariff policies are economically
illiterate, how they're based on
fundamental misunderstandings of trade
and will end up hurting American workers
and consumers. But I'm equally critical
of Democrats who promise the world
without a realistic plan to finance it.
Now, let's talk about what's happening
during the shutdown because I think it
reveals some important truths about
priorities and power. According to CBS
News reporting from midocctober, the
Trump administration found a way to
continue paying military personnel
during the shutdown by tapping unused
research and development funds. The FBI
also continued to be paid. These are the
administration argues essential
functions. House Speaker Mike Johnson
warned that this was a temporary fix and
that troops might miss their next
paychecks if the shutdown continues. I
want you to think about what this tells
us. The government can find ways to pay
the military and law enforcement even
during a shutdown. But hundreds of
thousands of other federal workers,
people who inspect our food, who process
social security applications, who
maintain our national parks, who do the
daily work of keeping the government
functioning. They're either furled or
working without pay. Federal
contractors, many of whom are low-wage
workers, janitors, security guards, food
service workers, they're not working at
all and they won't receive back pay when
the shutdown ends. This reflects a set
of priorities that I find deeply
troubling. We can always find money for
the military, for law enforcement, for
the security apparatus, but programs
that help ordinary people, those are
always the first things on the chopping
block when there's a budget fight. This
isn't an accident. It reflects the power
structure of American society. The
defense contractors, the security state,
the wealthy individuals and corporations
who benefit from low taxes. They have
enormous political influence. Working
people, the poor, the elderly, they have
much less. And you know, for those of
you who are my age or older who remember
the 1960s and 70s, I think you'll
recognize that America has changed in
fundamental ways. Back then, we had much
higher taxes on the wealthy. the top
marginal tax rate was 70% or more. We
had stronger unions that gave workers
real bargaining power. We had a
political system that uh while certainly
not perfect, was much more responsive to
the needs of ordinary citizens than it
is today. And as a result, we had less
inequality, stronger economic growth
that was more widely shared and a
government that actually functioned
reasonably well most of the time. What
happened? Well, starting in the 1980s
with the Reagan administration and
continuing through both Democratic and
Republican presidents. Since then, we've
had a systematic dismantling of the
institutions and policies that created
broadly shared prosperity. We've cut
taxes on the wealthy and corporations
again and again. We've weakened unions
and allowed corporations to ship jobs
overseas. We've deregulated industries
in ways that increase profits for
shareholders while hurting workers and
consumers. We've allowed money to flood
into politics to an extent that would
have been unimaginable 50 years ago. And
the result is that we now have levels of
economic inequality not seen since the
1920s. A political system that is
increasingly unresponsive to the needs
of ordinary citizens and a government
that lurches from crisis to crisis,
unable to address even basic functions
like passing a budget on time. This
shutdown is a symptom of that broader
dysfunction. Both parties are more
interested in positioning themselves for
political advantage than in actually
solving problems. The Republicans want
to look fiscally responsible without
actually being fiscally responsible. The
Democrats want to look like they're
fighting for health care without
actually reforming the health care
system. And meanwhile, the American
people suffer the consequences. Federal
workers go without paychecks. Essential
services are disrupted. and the rest of
the world looks at the United States and
wonders what happened to the country
that used to be a model of stable
effective governance. Now, I want to
talk about something that I think is
particularly important for understanding
this moment and that's the broader
context of American decline. I don't say
that to be pessimistic or to engage in
the kind of doommongering that's become
fashionable in some circles. I say it
because I think we need to be cleareyed
about where we are and what needs to
change. The United States is still the
world's largest economy, still the
world's most powerful military force,
still a center of innovation and
technological development, but our
position is eroding and not primarily
because of external threats, but because
of our own choices. Uh, China's economy
has grown to rival ours in size and is
on track to surpass it within the next
decade or two. This isn't because China
is cheating or stealing despite what you
hear from politicians in both parties.
It's because they've invested heavily in
education, in infrastructure, in
research and development. While we've
wasted trillions on wars and tax cuts
for the rich, India is emerging as
another major economic power. The
European Union, despite its own
problems, has maintained social
protections and public investments that
we've been cutting. Even smaller
countries are outperforming us on
measures of social well-being,
education, health care, life expectancy.
This isn't inevitable. It's the result
of policy choices. And one of those
choices, one that both parties share
responsibility for, is this habit of
governing by crisis, of lurching from
one shutdown threat to the next, of
treating the basic functions of
government as bargaining chips in
political games. No other advanced
economy does this. Parliamentary systems
in Europe, in Canada, in Australia, they
have their problems and their political
conflicts, but they don't shut down
their governments over budget disputes.
They have mechanisms for resolving these
issues without disrupting essential
services. The fact that we keep doing
this, that we've had more than 20
government shutdowns since the 1980s,
tells you something about how our
political system has broken down. And I
think this is something that older
Americans especially understand because
you remember a time when things worked
better. You remember when Democrats and
Republicans could disagree, sometimes
sharply, but still find ways to
compromise and keep the government
functioning. Uh you remember when we
built the interstate highway system,
when we put a man on the moon, when we
created Medicare and Social Security,
when we passed landmark civil rights
legislation, these were major
achievements that required political
courage and compromise. What's different
now? Why can't we do those things
anymore? Well, part of it is the rise of
what I call ideological extremism on
both sides, though I think it's more
pronounced on the Republican side in
recent years. The idea that compromise
is betrayal, that working with the other
side is selling out, that politics is
war by other means. This is poison for
democratic governance. Democracy
requires compromise. It requires the
ability to see the other side as
legitimate opponents rather than enemies
to be destroyed. When you lose that, you
get paralysis and dysfunction. Uh but
there's another factor that I think is
even more important, and that's the
influence of money in politics. The
Citizens United decision and subsequent
rulings have allowed unlimited money to
flow into our political system. Wealthy
individuals and corporations can now
spend as much as they want to influence
elections and policy. And the result is
that politicians are much more
responsive to their donors than to their
constituents. Both parties are guilty of
this. Democrats take money from Wall
Street, from tech companies, from
Hollywood. Republicans take money from
fossil fuel companies, from defense
contractors, from wealthy individuals.
And in both cases, this money shapes
policy in ways that benefit the donors
rather than ordinary Americans. This is
why we can't have a rational discussion
about fiscal policy because a rational
fiscal policy would involve raising
taxes on the wealthy and corporations,
cutting military spending, implementing
cost controls on health care, investing
in education and infrastructure. But all
of those things would hurt powerful
interests that fund political campaigns.
So instead, we get theater. we get
shutdown fights that are really about
messaging and positioning rather than
about actually solving problems. Now,
some people might say I'm being too
cynical, that I'm not giving enough
credit to the genuine policy differences
between the parties. And yes, there are
real differences. Democrats generally
favor more social spending, more
regulation, higher taxes on the wealthy.
Republicans generally favor lower taxes,
less regulation, more military spending.
These are legitimate differences that
reflect different values and different
views about the role of government. But
here's the thing. When you look at what
actually happens when either party is in
power, uh the differences are much
smaller than the rhetoric suggests.
Democrats talk about raising taxes on
the wealthy. But when they're in power,
they often settle for modest increases
that don't fundamentally change the
distribution of income. Republicans talk
about cutting spending, but when they're
in power, they increase military
spending and pass tax cuts that explode
the deficit. Both parties talk about
reforming health care, but neither has
been willing to take on the insurance
companies and pharmaceutical
corporations that profit from the
current system. Why? Because both
parties are ultimately serving the same
masters, the wealthy donors and
corporate interests that fund their
campaigns. This is why I've been so
critical of American foreign policy
under both Democratic and Republican
administrations. We maintain hundreds of
military bases around the world. We
intervene in countries that pose no
threat to us. We support authoritarian
regimes when it suits our interests, all
in service of what we call the
rules-based international order, but
what is really an American-led empire
that serves corporate interests. I've
written about this extensively. When
Trump imposed his tariff policies, which
I've described as childish and
economically illiterate, I pointed out
that the real problem isn't trade
deficits. its fiscal deficits caused by
tax cuts for the rich and excessive
military spending. And America's trade
deficit is not because other countries
are cheating us despite what Trump
claims. It's because our government
spends far more than it takes in. And
that excess demand gets met through
imports. This is basic macroeconomics
that any firstear economics student
should understand. But admitting that
would require confronting powerful
interests. It would require saying that
maybe we don't need to spend more on the
military than the next 10 countries
combined. Maybe we don't need to
maintain an empire of bases around the
world. Maybe we should tax wealthy
individuals and corporations at the
rates we did in the 1950s and60s when
the economy was growing rapidly and
inequality was much lower. Maybe we
should implement the kind of health care
system that every other advanced economy
has which would save us trillions of
dollars while providing better care to
more people. These are the conversations
we should be having. But instead, we get
shut down theater. We get politicians
from both parties posturing for their
base, accusing the other side of
extremism while refusing to address the
fundamental problems. And the American
people, especially those of you who have
lived through decades of this
dysfunction, you're rightfully
frustrated and angry. Now, I I want to
address something specific that came up
during the shutdown, which is the
question of whether the president can
unilaterally direct funds to pay the
military. According to news reports,
Trump used unused research and
development funds to ensure military
paychecks continued. Some Democrats
questioned whether this was legal. And
you know what? That's actually an
important constitutional question about
the separation of powers and
congressional control over spending. But
here's what struck me about that debate.
Democrats seem more concerned about the
legality of paying troops than about the
troops not getting paid. Now, maybe
that's not entirely fair. Maybe they
were making a principled argument about
constitutional constraints on executive
power. And those constraints do matter.
We don't want presidents to be able to
spend money however they want without
congressional approval. That's an
important check on executive authority.
But the optics were terrible. It made
Democrats look like they cared more
about procedural objections than about
military families. And this gets at
something I've observed throughout my
career, which is that Democrats are
often very good at making technically
correct arguments that are politically
tonedeaf. They're right on the merits,
but they lose the messaging battle
because they can't communicate in
simple, direct terms that resonate with
ordinary people. Republicans are often
better at this, though their messages
are frequently based on falsehoods.
They're good at simple narratives.
Democrats want to spend your money.
Republicans want to let you keep it.
Democrats want big government.
Republicans want freedom. These
narratives are oversimplified to the
point of being misleading, but they're
effective because they're simple and
they appeal to basic values. Democrats
need to learn how to communicate their
values just as effectively. Instead of
getting into technical arguments about
the Affordable Care Act subsidy
mechanisms, they should be saying every
American deserves health care, period.
We're the richest country in the world
and we're the only advanced economy that
doesn't guarantee this basic right.
That's a moral failing and we're going
to fix it. That's a message people can
understand and rally behind. Similarly,
instead of defending every penny of
federal spending as if it's all equally
important, Democrats should be saying,
"Yes, we need to get our fiscal house in
order, and we're going to do it by
making the wealthy pay their fair share,
by cutting wasteful military spending,
by implementing cost controls on health
care. We're not going to do it by
cutting social security or Medicare or
education or infrastructure. That's a
clear principled position that addresses
legitimate concerns about deficits while
protecting the programs people depend
on. Republicans, meanwhile, need to stop
pretending that you can cut taxes,
increase military spending, and balance
the budget all at the same time. The
math doesn't work. It's never worked.
Every time they've tried it, from Reagan
to Bush to Trump, deficits have
exploded. If they're serious about
fiscal responsibility, they need to be
honest about the tradeoffs. You can't
have Swedish level public services with
Texas level taxes. You have to choose.
Now, I know some of you watching this
might be thinking, "Okay, Professor
Saxs, you've told us what's wrong, but
what's the solution? How do we fix
this?" And I want to be honest with you,
there are no easy answers. The problems
we're facing are deep and structural.
They can't be fixed with one election or
one piece of legislation. They require
sustained political effort over many
years. But I can outline what I think
needs to happen. First, we need
fundamental campaign finance reform. We
need to get money out of politics or at
least greatly reduce its influence. This
probably requires a constitutional
amendment to overturn Citizens United
and related decisions. It means public
financing of campaigns, strict limits on
donations, disclosure requirements for
all political spending. Without this, we
can't have a democracy that's responsive
to ordinary citizens rather than wealthy
donors. Second, we need tax reform that
returns us to something closer to the
progressive taxation we had in the mid
20th century. The top marginal tax rate
should be at least 50%, probably higher.
Capital gains should be taxed as
ordinary income. We should have a wealth
tax on the very richest Americans.
Estate taxes should be much higher to
prevent the emergence of a hereditary
aristocracy. And yes, we probably need
to raise some taxes on the middle class,
too, but only in the context of
providing universal health care and
other benefits that would more than
offset the increased taxes. Third, we
need to drastically cut military
spending. We should close most of our
overseas bases, end our involvement in
foreign conflicts that have nothing to
do with American security, and refocus
our military on actual defense rather
than global power projections. This
could easily save three to 400 billion a
year, which could be redirected to
domestic priorities. Fourth, we need
comprehensive health care reform.
Medicare for all, a singlepayer system,
whatever you want to call it, but
something that guarantees health care as
a right while implementing the cost
controls that every other country uses.
This would actually save money in the
long run while providing better care to
more people. Fifth, we need massive
public investment in infrastructure,
both traditional infrastructure like
roads and bridges and 21st century
infrastructure like uh broadband
internet and clean energy. These
investments pay for themselves over time
through increased productivity and
economic growth. Sixth, we need to
strengthen workers rights and rebuild
unions. This isn't just about fairness,
though that matters. It's about
rebalancing power in our economy. When
workers have real bargaining power,
wages rise, inequality falls, and demand
increases in ways that drive economic
growth. Seventh, we need serious action
on climate change. This isn't optional.
It's an existential threat and the
longer we wait, the more expensive and
difficult it becomes. We need a massive
mobilization comparable to what we did
in World War II, transitioning our
entire economy to clean energy within
the next two decades. These are big,
ambitious goals. They would require
political courage and sustained effort.
They would face fierce opposition from
wealthy individuals and corporations
whose interests would be threatened, but
they're achievable. Other countries have
done similar things. We did similar
things in the past. There's no reason we
can't do them now except for political
will. And this brings me to what I think
is the most important point. Change
won't come from politicians in
Washington. It never does. Real change
in a democracy comes from organized
citizens demanding it. The New Deal
happened because workers organized and
fought for it. Civil rights legislation
happened because activists organized and
fought for it. Social Security and
Medicare happened because older
Americans organized and fought for them.
If we want to fix American governance,
if we want to end this cycle of
shutdowns and dysfunction, if we want a
government that actually serves the
interests of ordinary people rather than
wealthy donors, we need to organize and
fight for it. That means getting
involved in politics at every level,
from local school boards to Congress. It
means supporting candidates who refuse
corporate money and advocate for the
reforms I've outlined. It means building
movements that can pressure politicians
to do the right thing even when it's
politically difficult. For those of you
who are older, who remember when America
worked better, I know this can feel
daunting. You've seen so many promises
broken, so many movements that failed to
achieve their goals. But I also know
that you have wisdom and experience that
younger generations need. You remember
what's possible. You remember when we
could do big things, and your voice
matters perhaps now more than ever. This
government shutdown, frustrating as it
is, is ultimately a symptom of much
larger problems. Both parties share
responsibility for where we are. Both
parties need to change it. And that
change will only happen if we demand it.
The alternative is continued decline,
continued dysfunction, continued erosion
of the democratic institutions that
previous generations built and defended.
We can do better. We must do better. The
future of American democracy depends on
it. Thank you for listening. I know
these are difficult topics and I've been
quite critical of both parties, but I
believe that honest, cleareyed analysis
is essential if we're going to move
forward. We can't solve problems we're
not willing to acknowledge and we can't
have the future we want unless we're
willing to fight for it. I hope this has
given you some clarity about what's
really happening in Washington and why
it matters. The stakes couldn't be
higher. Our democracy, our prosperity,
our future as a nation all depend on
whether we can summon the political will
to make the changes we need. I believe
we can. The question is whether we